When I was lying there
in the VA hospital,
with a big hole blown through
the middle of my life,
I started having
these dreams of flying.
I was free.
Sooner or later, though,
you always have to wake up.
In cryo, you don't
dream at all.
It doesn't feel like 6 years.
More like a 5th of tequila
and an ass-kicking.
Tommy was the scientist,
not me.
He was the one who wanted to
get shot light-years out in space
to find the answers.
Are we there yet?
Yeah, we're there, sunshine.
We're there.
It's about your brother.
So, a week before
Tommy's gonna ship out,
a guy with a gun
ends his journey
for the paper in his wallet.
You've been in cryo for 5 years,
9 months and 22 days.
You will be hungry.
You will be weak.
If you feel nausea,
please use the sacks...
Yeah, Tommy was the scientist.
Me, I'm just another dumb grunt going
someplace he's gonna regret.
Up ahead was Pandora.
You grew up hearing about it,
but I never figured
I'd be going there.
Your brother represented
a significant investment.
We'd like to talk to you
about taking over his contract.
And since your genome is
identical to his,
you could step into his shoes,
so to speak.
It'd be a fresh start
on a new world.
And the pay is good.
Very good.
Exo-packs on! Let's go!
Exo-packs on!
Remember, people,
you lose that mask,
you're unconscious
in 20 seconds,
you're dead in 4 minutes!
Let's nobody be dead today!
Looks very bad on my report.
Hell's Gate tower,
this is TAV 1-6 on approach.
Crossing outer marker.
Mine is in sight.
One life ends,
another begins.
Harnesses off!
Get your packs!
Put it together, let's go! Let's go!
Harnesses off. 1 minute!
When that ramp comes down,
go directly into the base. Do not stop!
Go straight inside.
Wait for my mark!
Go, go, go, go!
Get out of there!
Keep moving!
Let's go, let's go!
There's no such thing
as an ex-Marine.
You may be out,
but you never lose the attitude.
I told myself I could pass
any test a man could pass.
They can fix a spinal,
if you got the money,
but not on vet benefits,
not in this economy.
Let's go, special case!
Do not make me wait for you!
Well, well, ladies.
Look at all this fresh meat!
Back on Earth, these guys
were Army dogs, Marines,
fighting for freedom.
Look out, hot rod!
But out here
they're just hired guns,
taking the money,
working for the company.
Check this out, man.
Meals on wheels.
Man, that is just wrong.
I got 2 guys free
in about 20 minutes!
Got it! Need them!
You're not in Kansas anymore.
You are on Pandora,
ladies and gentlemen.
Respect that fact
every second of every day.
If there is a hell,
you might want to go there
for some R&R
after a tour on Pandora.
Out there, beyond that fence,
every living thing that crawls,
flies or squats in the mud
wants to kill you and
eat your eyes for Jujubes.
We have an indigenous population
of humanoids called the Na'vi.
They're fond of arrows
dipped in a neurotoxin
that'll stop your heart
in one minute.
And they have bones reinforced with
naturally occurring carbon fiber.
They are very hard
to kill.
As head of security,
it is my job to keep you alive.
I will not succeed.
Not with all of you.
If you wish to survive,
you need to cultivate
a strong mental attitude.
You've got to obey the rules.
Pandora rules.
Rule number 1...
There's nothing like
an old-school safety brief
to put your mind at ease.
Excuse me.
Excuse me. Jake!
You're Jake, right?
Tom's brother.
You look just like him.
Sorry, I'm Norm.
Spellman.
I went through avatar training
with him.
...into the bio-lab.
We're gonna spend
a lot of time up here.
Hey! How you doing?
Norm, avatar driver.
Hi.
Hey.
Link... Here's the link room
right here.
This is where we're connecting
to the avatar.
Me and Norm are here to drive
these remotely controlled bodies
called avatars.
And they're grown from human DNA
mixed with the DNA of the natives.
Hey. Welcome.
Hey.
Welcome to Pandora.
Good to have you.
Thanks.
Damn! They got big.
Yeah, they fully mature
on the flight out.
So the proprioceptive sims
seem to work really well.
Yeah, they've got
great muscle tone.
It'll take us a few hours
to get them decanted,
but you guys can take them
out tomorrow.
There's yours.
Hey. Dr. Norm Spellman.
Dr. Max Patel. Great to meet you.
Good to meet you, yeah.
Looks like him.
No, it looks like you.
This is your avatar now, Jake.
And the concept is that every driver
is matched to his own avatar,
so that their nervous systems
are in tune,
or something.
Which is why they
offered me the gig,
because I can link
with Tommy's avatar,
which is insanely expensive.
Is this right? I just say
whatever to the video log?
Yeah, we gotta get in the habit
of documenting everything.
You know, what we see,
what we feel.
It's all part
of the science.
And good science
is good observation.
Plus it'll help to keep you sane
for the next 6 years.
All right.
Whatever.
So...
Well, here I am,
doing science.
They're coming out!
Attention. Drivers coming out of link.
God.
Where's the lab coat?
Who's got my goddamn
cigarette?
Guys! What's wrong
with this picture?
Thank you!
Grace Augustine is a legend.
She's the head of the Avatar Program.
She wrote the book,
I mean, literally wrote the book
on Pandoran botany.
Well, that's 'cause she likes
plants better than people.
Here she is,
Cinderella back from the ball.
Grace, I'd like you to meet
Norm Spellman and Jake Sully.
Norm. I hear good things about you.
How's your Na'vi?
Grace?
This is Jake Sully.
Ma'am.
Yeah, yeah.
I know who you are,
and I don't need you.
I need your brother.
You know, the PhD who trained
for 3 years for this mission?
He's dead.
I know it's a big inconvenience
for everyone.
How much lab training
have you had?
I dissected a frog once.
You see? You see?
I mean, they're just pissing on us
without even the courtesy of
calling it rain.
I'm going to Selfridge.
No, Grace,
I don't think that's a good idea.
No, man, this is such bullshit!
I'm gonna kick
his corporate butt.
He has no business sticking
his nose in my department.
Here tomorrow, 0800.
Try and use big words.
Scorpion 2-Hotel,
Hell's Gate tower.
You are cleared
for south departure.
Hover taxi, Delta runway.
Squawk ident.
You see that?
Yes, sir.
No, you didn't.
You were looking at the monitor.
I love this putter, Ronnie!
I love this putter.
Parker, you know, I used to
think it was benign neglect,
but now I see that you're
intentionally screwing me.
Grace, you know,
I enjoy our little talks.
I need a researcher.
Not some jarhead dropout.
Well, actually,
I thought we got lucky with him.
Lucky?
Yeah.
How is this
in any way lucky?
Lucky your guy
had a twin brother,
and lucky that brother wasn't
some oral hygienist or something.
A Marine we can use.
I'm assigning him to your team
as security escort.
The last thing I need is another
trigger-happy moron out there!
Look, look, you're supposed
to be winning the hearts
and the minds
of the natives.
Isn't that the whole point
of your little puppet show?
If you look like them
and you talk like them,
then they'll start trusting us.
We build them a school,
we teach them English,
but after, what,
how many years?
Relations with the indigenous
are only getting worse.
Yeah, that tends to happen
when you use
machine guns on them.
Right. Come here.
I can't...
This is why we're here.
Unobtanium.
Because this little gray rock
sells for 20 million a kilo.
That's the only reason.
It's what pays for the whole party.
It's what pays
for your science.
Comprendo?
Now, those savages are
threatening our whole operation,
we're on the brink of war,
and you're supposed to be finding
a diplomatic solution.
So use what you've got,
and get me some results.
So, how much link time
have you logged?
About 520 hours.
That's good.
You're in there.
You're here.
How much have you logged?
Zip. But I read a manual.
Tell me you're joking.
This is cool.
Let's go.
Don't. I got this.
So you just figured
you'd come out here,
to the most hostile environment
known to man,
with no training of any kind,
and see how it went?
What was going
through your head?
Maybe I was sick of doctors
telling me what I couldn't do.
Biometrics are good.
Link 3 is ready.
Keep your arms in, hands in,
head down.
Down. Just relax and let
your mind go blank.
That shouldn't be
hard for you.
Kiss the darkest part
of my lily white...
Initiate link.
Run sequence unit 3. Go.
Launching.
I have the first congruency.
That's a gorgeous brain.
Nice activity.
Go figure.
Phase-lock 40%.
All right.
Going in.
I'm going in in 4.
Phase-lock 99%.
Link is stable.
He's in.
Jake, can you hear me?
Can you hear me, Jake?
Pupillary reflex is good.
Pinna response normal.
How you feeling, Jake?
Hey, guys.
Welcome to your new body, Jake.
Good!
Yeah, we're gonna take this
nice and easy, Jake.
And touch your thumb
to your fingers. Yeah.
Thumb to your fingers.
No problem.
That's good. I can see
you can remember that one.
Got it.
Well, if you want
to sit up,
that's fine.
Okay, good. Just take it
nice and slow, Jake. Good.
Okay, well, no truncal ataxia,
that's good.
Are you feeling lightheaded
or dizzy at all?
You're wiggling
your toes!
Good. Good, Jake. That's great.
Distal motor control is good.
Good, Jake.
Are you feeling
any numbness or pain?
That's great, Jake. Hold on, now.
Take it easy.
Don't get ahead of yourself, okay?
There's a few more sensory motor
reflex tests we need to run,
so take it easy.
Wait.
Jake.
Sit down, Jake.
Jake! Listen to me. Jake!
I need you to sit down.
Jake! It's okay.
Buddy, listen to me.
It's all good. I got this.
Jake, you need
to sit down right now.
Guys, get him back
on the gurney now.
Listen to me. For your own safety,
you need to sit down.
You need time to adjust
to the avatar... Jake!
God, Jake, watch your tail.
Yeah!
Sedate! Sedate him!
1,000 milligrams of Supitocam! Stat!
Guys! Guys!
By the numbers.
Jake. Come on.
Jake! Listen to me.
You're not used
to your avatar body.
This is dangerous.
This is great.
Jake? Jake, listen to me. Come on.
They're gonna put you out.
Norm, sit down.
No, no. I gotta get
out of these leads.
God damn it!
Bring them home!
Norm! Do not leave control!
You're not ready for it!
Come on,
you ain't got no skills.
So close!
I don't even have
to play defense on it.
Hey, guys. Hey.
It's okay, I'll get him.
Jake, you have to come back!
Jake! Jake!
Excuse me.
Watch it!
Sorry!
Come on!
Jake! We're not supposed
to be running!
Jeez! Sorry.
Watch it!
Hey, Marine!
Damn.
Grace?
Well, who'd you
expect, numbnuts?
Think fast.
Motor control's
looking good.
Come on, everybody,
quiet down!
All right, gang, lights out.
Come on, Louise,
chop-chop.
Hey, hey, hey!
Don't play with that,
you'll go blind.
That's kind of freaky.
Come on. Scat.
Good night.
Lights out!
See you at dinner, kiddies.
Welcome back.
You okay? You all right?
Yeah, I'm okay.
I'm Trudy.
I fly all the science sorties.
And this here is my baby.
Hold on a second.
Hey, Wainfleet!
Get it done!
We bounce at zero-nine.
Yeah, I'm on it, capitaine!
Vine strike's still loose.
You guys are packing
some heavy gear.
Watch it!
Yeah, that's 'cause we're not the
only thing flying around out there.
Or the biggest.
I'm gonna need you on a door gun.
I'm a man short.
I thought you'd never ask.
There's your man.
See you on the flight line.
You wanted to see me, Colonel?
This low gravity'll make you soft.
You get soft,
Pandora will shit you out dead
with zero warning.
I pulled your record, Corporal.
Venezuela, that was
some mean bush.
Nothing like this here, though.
You got some heart, kid,
showing up in this neighborhood.
I figured it's just another hellhole.
I was First Recon myself.
A few years ahead of you.
Well, maybe more than a few.
3 tours Nigeria, not a scratch.
I come out here?
Day 1. Think I felt like
a shavetail louie?
Yeah. They could fix me up,
if I rotated back.
Yeah, and make me
pretty again.
But you know what?
I kind of like it.
It reminds me every day
what's waiting out there.
Hup! The Avatar Program
is a bad joke.
Bunch of limp-dick
science majors.
However,
it does present an opportunity
both timely
and unique. Clear!
Clear!
A recon gyrene in an avatar body.
That's a potent mix.
Give me the goose bumps.
Such a Marine could provide
the intel I need,
right on the ground.
Right in
the hostiles' camp.
Look, Sully. I want you to
learn these savages from the inside.
I want you to gain their trust.
I need to know how to force
their cooperation
or hammer them hard
if they won't.
Am I still
with Augustine?
On paper.
Yeah, you walk like one of her
science pukes, you quack like one,
but you report to me.
Can you do that
for me, son?
Hell, yeah, sir.
Well, all right, then.
Son, I take care of my own.
You get me what I need,
I'll see to it you get your legs back
when you rotate home.
Your real legs.
That sounds real good, sir.
Link's ready!
Phase-lock 40%.
Just keep your mouth shut
and let Norm do the talking.
I have 5 congruencies.
Phase-lock 90%.
Link 3 ready.
All right, I'm going in.
Shut it down.
We're gonna stay a while.
Norm! Your pack.
Pack.
Stay with the ship.
One idiot with a gun is enough.
You the man, Doc.
Prolemuris.
They're not aggressive.
Relax, Marine.
You're making me nervous.
So, how will
they know we're here?
I'm sure they're
watching us right now.
Keep moving, Norm.
Keep up, guys!
And here I go.
Scanning.
It's that fast?
Amazing, isn't it?
Yeah.
So, that is signal transduction
from this root
to the root of
the tree next to it.
So, we should
take a sample.
Okay. Sample.
You know, it's probably electrical,
based on the speed
of the reaction.
Norm, you've contaminated
the sample with your saliva.
Right.
So, here I go.
Don't shoot. Don't shoot,
you'll piss him off.
It's already pissed off.
Jake, that armor's too thick.
Trust me.
It's a territorial threat display.
Do not run, or he'll charge.
So, what do I do,
dance with it?
Just hold your ground.
Yeah? Come on!
What you got?
Yeah. Who's bad?
That's right.
Yeah, that's what
I'm talking about, bitch.
That's right, get your punk ass
back to mommy.
Yeah? Yeah, you got nothing.
You keep running.
Yeah, and why don't you bring back
some of your friends?
Shit.
So what about this one?
Run? Don't run? What?
Run! Definitely run!
I'm gonna have
to call it, guys.
We're not allowed to run night ops.
Colonel's orders.
I'm sorry, Doc, he's just gonna
have to hang on till morning.
He won't make it till morning.
I don't have
all goddamn night.
Come on!
Hey, wait. Don't!
Great.
Look, I know you probably
don't understand this,
but thank you.
Thank you.
That was
pretty impressive.
I would have been screwed
if you hadn't come along. It was...
Hey, wait a second.
Hey, where you going?
Wait up!
Just... Hey, slow down.
Look, wait up, I just wanted to
say thanks for killing those things.
Damn!
Don't thank.
You don't thank
for this.
This is sad.
Very sad only.
Okay. Okay.
I'm sorry.
Whatever I did,
I am sorry.
All this is your fault.
They did not need to die.
My fault? They attacked me.
How am I the bad guy?
Your fault!
Easy. Easy.
You're like a baby.
Making noise, don't know what to do.
Easy.
Fine. Fine.
If you love your little
forest friends,
why not let them
just kill my ass?
What's the thinking?
Why save you?
Yeah. Yeah, why save me?
You have a strong heart.
No fear.
But stupid!
Ignorant like a child.
Well, if I'm like a child, then...
Look, maybe you should
teach me.
Sky People cannot learn.
You do not See.
Well, then teach me
how to See.
No one can teach you to See.
Look, come on, can't we talk?
Say, where'd you learn
to speak English?
Dr. Augustine's school?
You're like a baby.
I need your help.
You should not be here.
Okay, take me with you.
No! Go back.
No.
Go back.
No!
What...
What are they?
Seeds of the Sacred Tree.
Very pure spirits.
What was that all about?
Come.
Come!
Where are we going?
Come.
What's your name?
Shit!
Okay.
What's going on?
Wait.
What's happening?
Hey!
What's he saying?
Hey, what's he saying?
My father is deciding
whether to kill you.
Your father.
It's nice to meet you, sir.
That is Mother.
She is Tsahik. The one
who interprets the will of Eywa.
Who's Eywa?
What are you called?
Jake Sully.
Why did you
come to us?
I came to learn.
We have tried to teach other
Sky People.
It is hard to fill a cup
which is already full.
Well, my cup is empty,
trust me.
Just ask Dr. Augustine.
I'm no scientist.
What are you?
I was a Marine. A...
A warrior of
the Jarhead clan.
It is decided. My daughter
will teach you our ways.
Learn well,
Jakesully.
Then we will see if your insanity
can be cured.
Good evening.
Please don't get up.
Excuse me.
Sorry.
Hey, how you doing?
Jake. Jake!
He's in alpha.
He's coming out
right now.
Jake. Jake!
Come on back, kid.
Come on. That's it.
There you go.
You're okay.
Damn! You were
dug in like a tick.
Is the avatar safe?
Yeah, Doc.
And you are not
gonna believe where I am.
The last thing we see
is this Marine's ass
disappearing into the brush with
this angry thanator coming after him.
Hey, it's not something
you can teach.
That is awesome.
You know, for reasons
I cannot fathom,
the Omaticaya have chosen you.
God help us all.
"Jarhead clan"?
And it worked?
Hey, I'm practically family.
They're gonna study me.
I have to learn to be one of them.
That's called
taking the initiative, son.
I wish I had 10 more like you.
Look, Sully. Sully.
Just find out what
the blue monkeys want.
You know, I mean, we try to give
them medicine, education, roads.
But no, no, they like mud.
And that wouldn't bother me,
it's just that they're...
Hey, can you...
Can somebody just... Sector 12.
Okay, go, go, go,
stop. Stop...
Rich, stop!
That's... Jesus!
Their damn village
happens to be resting on
the richest unobtanium deposit
within 200 klicks in any direction.
I mean, look at all that cheddar!
Well, who gets them to move?
Guess.
What if they won't go?
I'm betting that they will.
Okay, okay, hey.
Look. Look.
Killing the indigenous
looks bad,
but there's one thing that
shareholders hate more than bad press,
and that's a bad
quarterly statement.
I didn't make
up the rules.
So just find me a carrot
that'll get them to move,
otherwise it's gonna
have to be all stick. Okay?
You got 3 months.
That's when the 'dozers get there.
Well, we're wasting time.
I like this guy.
Guys, right now...
Okay, let's run through them again.
Mo'at. Dragon lady.
Eytucan. Eytukan.
He's the clan leader.
But she's the spiritual leader.
Like a shaman.
Got it.
T'su'tey.
Tsu'tey.
He'll be the next clan leader.
Neytiri.
She'll be the next Tsahik.
They become a mated pair.
So who's this Eywa?
Who's Eywa?
Only their deity. Their goddess,
made up of all living things.
Everything they know!
You'd know this if you had
any training whatsoever.
Who's got a date
with the chief's daughter?
Come on. That's...
All right, knock it off, you two.
Let's go.
Village life starts early.
Don't do anything
unusually stupid.
Easy, boy.
Pale is female.
Okay. Easy, girl.
That is tsaheylu.
The bond.
Feel her.
Feel her heartbeat.
Her breath.
Feel her strong legs.
You may tell her what to do.
Inside.
For now, say where to go.
Forward!
You should go away.
No, you'd miss me.
I knew you could speak English.
Again.
If you want to hit this thing,
it's gonna be complicated.
Your scan doesn't show
the internal structure.
There's an outer row of columns.
Real heavy duty.
There's a secondary ring here,
and an inner ring.
There's a core structure
like a spiral.
That's how they move
up and down.
We're gonna need accurate scans
on every column.
Roger that.
What else can you tell us about
the structure?
I'm guessing this secondary ring,
that's also load-bearing.
So where are we going?
Getting out of Dodge.
I'm not about to let Selfridge and
Quaritch micro-manage this thing.
There's a mobile link up at Site 26
we can work out of,
way up in the mountains.
The Hallelujah Mountains?
That's right.
Are you serious?
Yeah.
Yes!
The legendary floating mountains
of Pandora.
Heard of them?
We're getting close.
Yeah, look at my instruments.
Yep. We're in the Flux Vortex.
We're VFR from here on.
What's VFR?
Means you gotta see
where you're going.
You can't see anything.
Exactly. Ain't that a bitch?
My God.
You should see your faces.
Thank you for
flying Air Pandora.
Welcome to camp.
So, this is my bunk.
This stuff is nasty.
Norm, go under.
All right.
Grace didn't miss a thing.
Trudy, you'll take the top one.
She knew I was talking
to the Colonel.
But I had what she needed,
a way back in with the clan,
so she's playing nice.
All right. Jake, hang a left.
You'll be in the link at the end.
Unit 1. Beulah.
She's the least glitchy.
Holy shit!
Do not look in her eye.
Ikran is not horse.
Once tsaheylu is made,
ikran will fly with only 1 hunter
in the whole life.
To become taronyu,
hunter,
you must choose your own ikran
and he must choose you.
When?
When you are ready.
Okay. This is video log 12.
Time's 2132.
Do I have to do this now?
I really need to
get some rack.
No, now.
When it's fresh.
Okay, location, shack,
and the days are starting
to blur together.
The language is a pain,
but, you know,
I figure it's like
field-stripping a weapon.
Just repetition, repetition.
Navi.
"Nari."
Nari.
"Narrri"!
Narrri!
Txur ně'ul.
Stronger.
Neytiri calls me skxawng.
It means moron.
This is a very important
part of it.
Norm's attitude
has improved lately.
I see you. I see you.
But it's not just,
"I'm seeing you in front of me,"
it's "I see into you.
I See you."
It's good he's back on board,
but he thinks
I'm a skxawng, too.
"I'm accepting you.
I understand you."
So you gotta
get this, okay?
I gotta run! Okay?
Let's go.
My feet are getting tougher.
I can run farther every day.
I have to trust my body
to know what to do.
Yeah! Check it out!
Crap!
Every day it's reading the trails,
the tracks at the waterhole,
the tiniest scents and sounds.
She's always going on about the
flow of energy, the spirits of animals.
I really hope this tree-hugger
crap isn't on the final.
This isn't just about eye-hand
coordination out there, you know.
You need to listen
to what she says.
Try to see the forest
through her eyes.
Excuse me.
This is my video log here.
With Neytiri,
it's learn fast or die.
You gotta be kidding me.
I talked Mo'at into letting
Grace into the village.
It's the first time since
her school was closed down.
No, you don't.
Come back here.
Bon appétit.
Come on, Marine.
I'm trying to understand
this deep connection
the people have
to the forest.
She talks about
a network of energy
that flows through
all living things.
She says all energy
is only borrowed,
and one day you have
to give it back.
A clean kill.
You are ready.
Learning to ride an ikran,
we call them banshees,
is the test every
young hunter has to pass.
But to do that, you gotta go
where the banshees are.
Now what?
Jakesully will go first.
Now you choose your ikran.
This you must feel inside.
If he also chooses you,
move quick like I showed.
You will have one chance, Jake.
How will I know
if he chooses me?
He will try to kill you.
Outstanding.
Make the bond!
No!
Jake!
Tsaheylu, Jake.
Tsaheylu!
Stop!
Yeah, that's right.
You're mine.
First flight seals the bond.
You cannot wait.
Think, "Fly!"
Fly?
God damn!
Shit!
Shut up and fly straight!
That's it.
Bank left!
Level out!
That's it.
Jakesully!
Hey!
Let's go!
Yeah, baby, I got this!
Shit!
I may not be
much of a horse guy,
but I was born to do this.
Yeah!
I came like this.
This you. Yeah, yeah.
I turn. I feel the wind.
I turn very strong.
Look, yeah, see,
I banked so hard...
The Tree of Souls.
It's their most sacred place.
See the Flux Vortex
in these false color images?
Yeah, that's what messes up
my instruments.
There is something really interesting
going on in there biologically.
I would die to get samples.
Outsiders are strictly forbidden.
You lucky swine.
I was a stone-cold aerial hunter.
Death from above.
Only problem is,
you're not the only one.
Dive!
Go, go!
Follow me!
Our guys call it
a Great Leonopteryx.
It is Toruk.
Last Shadow.
Yeah, right.
It's the last one you ever see.
My grandfather's grandfather
was Toruk Macto.
Rider of Last Shadow.
He rode this?
Toruk chose him.
It has only happened 5 times
since the time of the First Songs.
That's a long time.
Yes.
Toruk Macto was mighty.
He brought the clans together
in a time of great sorrow.
All Na'vi people know the story.
Everything is backwards now.
Like out there is the true world
and in here is the dream.
It's hard to believe
it's only been 3 months.
I can barely remember
my old life.
I don't know who I am anymore.
Haven't gotten lost in the woods,
have you?
Your last report was
more than 2 weeks ago.
I'm starting to doubt
your resolve!
The way I see it,
it's time to terminate the mission.
No, I can do this.
You already have.
You give me good, usable intel.
This Tree of Souls place.
Yeah, I got them
by the balls with that
when this turns
into a shit fight,
which it will. Yeah.
Now it's time
to come in.
By the way,
you gonna get
your legs back.
Yeah. I got your corporate approval.
It's a done deal.
Gonna have you
on a shuttle tonight.
I'm a man of my word.
I gotta finish this.
There's one more thing.
Ceremony. It's the final stage
of becoming a man.
If I do it, I'm one of them.
And they'll trust me.
And I can negotiate
the terms of their relocation.
Well, then, you'd better
get it done, Corporal.
The Na'vi say that
every person is born twice.
The second time
is when you earn your place
among The People forever.
Come. Come.
This is a place for prayers
to be heard.
And sometimes answered.
We call these trees
Utraya Mokri.
The Tree of Voices.
The voices of our ancestors.
I can hear them.
They live, Jake,
within Eywa.
You are Omaticaya now.
You may make your bow
from the wood of Hometree.
And you may
choose a woman.
We have many
fine women.
Ninat is the best singer.
But I don't want Ninat.
Peyral is a good hunter.
Yeah, she is a good hunter.
I've already chosen.
But this woman must
also choose me.
She already has.
I am with you now, Jake.
We are mated for life.
What the hell
are you doing, Jake?
Ma Jake!
Don't forget your phase integration.
Jake! No, no, the middle button.
You gotta eat something.
Yeah, there you go.
Jake! Jake. Wake up!
Jake, please!
Don't make me
force-feed a cripple.
Grace, I don't want... Hey!
Jake!
Okay.
Here. I'm done.
Let's go.
And when was the last time
you took a shower?
I don't need a shower.
Jesus, Marine.
Jake!
Jake! Wake up!
Hey!
Stop! Stop!
Jake!
Go back, stop!
Hey, boss.
Hey!
What?
I got a native
doing the funky chicken here.
He's blocking my blade.
Well, keep going.
He'll move.
These people have to learn that
we don't stop. Come on, go, go, go.
Stop! Hey!
Go! Go!
There, see?
He moved.
Dude, dude!
Dude, no!
I'm blind.
Jake!
Neytiri!
Here, come on!
Freeze it right there.
Scale up.
Enhance.
Son of a bitch.
Unbelievable.
Get me a pilot.
Yes, sir.
You do not speak here!
Tsu'tey! Don't do this.
You! Listen. Brother...
You mated with this woman?
Shit.
Is this true?
We are mated before Eywa.
It is done.
Brother, please.
Do not attack the Sky People.
Many Omaticaya
will die if you do.
You are not my brother!
And I am not your enemy!
The enemy is out there,
and they are very powerful!
Go! Go! Go!
I can talk to them.
No more talk.
Tsu'tey!
I am Omaticaya.
I am one of you.
And I have the right to speak.
The words are like stones
in my heart.
Sir, I'm sorry. No! Hold on!
You can't interrupt
a link in progress!
It's very dangerous!
Grace!
No.
Wait!
Stay down, sir.
Okay. Look...
I was sent here to...
Are you out of
your goddamn mind?
You crossed the line.
Wheel this meat
out of here.
Jake! What the hell
is going on here?
You let me down, son.
So, what,
you find yourself
some local tail
and you just completely forget
what team you're playing for?
Parker, there is time
to salvage the situation.
Parker...
Shut your pie hole!
Or what, Ranger Rick?
You gonna shoot me?
I could do that.
You need to muzzle your dog.
Yeah, can we just take this down
a couple of notches, please?
You say you want to
keep your people alive?
You start by
listening to her.
Those trees were sacred to
the Omaticaya
in a way you can't imagine.
You know what?
You throw a stick
in the air around here,
it's gonna land
on some sacred fern,
for Christ's sake! I'm not talking
about some kind of pagan
voodoo here.
I'm talking about
something real,
something measurable
in the biology of the forest.
Which is what, exactly?
What we think we know
is that there is some kind of
electrochemical communication
between the roots
of the trees,
like the synapses
between neurons.
And each tree has 10-to-the-4th
connections to the trees around it.
And there are 10-to-the-12th
trees on Pandora.
Which is a lot,
I'm guessing.
It's more connections
than the human brain.
Get it?
It's a network.
It's a global network,
and the Na'vi can access it.
They can upload and download data.
Memories.
At sites like the one
you just destroyed.
Yes!
What the hell have you people
been smoking out there?
They're just goddamn trees!
You need to wake up, Parker.
No. You need to wake up.
The wealth of this world isn't
in the ground. It's all around us.
The Na'vi know that,
and they are fighting to defend it.
If you want to share
this world with them,
you need to
understand them.
I'd say we understand them just fine,
thanks to Jake here.
Hey, Doc, come take a look.
They're not gonna
give up their home.
make a deal.
For what? Lite beer?
And blue jeans?
There's nothing that we have
that they want.
Everything they sent me out here
to do is a waste of time.
They're never gonna
leave Hometree.
So, since a deal
can't be made,
I guess things
get real simple.
Jake, thanks.
I'm getting all emotional.
I might just give you
a big wet kiss.
I'll do it with minimal casualties
to the indigenous.
I'll drive them out with gas first.
It'll be humane.
More or less.
All right, let's pull the trigger.
Come on, people.
Man.
Let's pack it up, let's go.
This is how it's done.
When people are sitting
on shit that you want,
you make them your enemy.
Then you're justified in taking it.
Quaritch is rolling the gunships.
He's gonna hit Hometree.
My God.
Dr. Augustine!
You cannot be up here!
Back off!
Parker. Wait. Stop.
These are people you're about to...
No. No, no, no, no.
I said back off!
They're fly-bitten savages
that live in a tree!
All right?
Look around!
I don't know about you, but I see
a lot of trees! They can move!
Can you guys just please...
Yes, sir.
There are families in there.
There are children. Babies.
Are you gonna
kill children?
You don't want that kind of blood
on your hands. Believe me.
Just let me try
to talk them out.
They trust me.
Calibrate fast.
We're going in, right now.
Calibrating 3 and 4.
Run sequence.
Initiating. 30 seconds.
Listen to me.
You've got 1 hour.
Unless you want your girlfriend in there
when the ax comes down,
you get them to evacuate.
1 hour.
Look, tell them they're gonna
be here soon.
You have to leave, or you're gonna die.
Are you certain of this?
Look, they sent me here
to learn your ways
so one day I could bring this message
and that you would believe it.
What are you saying, Jake?
You knew this would happen?
Yes.
Look, at first
it was just orders,
and then
everything changed.
Okay? I fell in love.
I fell in love with the forest
and with the Omaticaya people.
And with you.
I trusted you.
With you. With you.
I trusted you!
Trust me now, please.
You will never be
one of The People!
I shouldn't have...
We tried to stop them!
Neytiri, please!
Please.
You have to go.
They're coming!
Time on target, 1 mike.
Copy. We have a visual.
Roger that.
Stay on heading 030.
Roger, 030.
Run to the forest!
They're coming!
They will destroy this place.
Neytiri, you must go now!
Run to the forest!
Run!
Run! Run!
No! God damn it, run!
That is one big damn tree.
Well, well, well.
I'd say diplomacy has failed.
All right, people,
let's get this done!
I want every gas round
you got right in the front door.
Roger.
CS .40's going hot.
Fire.
Firing.
Bingo.
Mighty good shooting, ace.
Sir, they've
opened fire.
You've got to be kidding me!
These dumb bastards
ain't getting the message.
All right,
let's turn up the heat.
Switch incendiaries!
Switching incendiaries.
Fire.
No!
And that's how
you scatter the roaches.
Neytiri!
We gotta move!
He's gonna blow the columns!
My God!
Mo'at! No!
If you are one of us,
help us.
All call signs, switch missiles.
Give me HE's at the base
of the west columns.
This way!
Rider section, switch missiles.
One's good.
2's rocks up.
3's up.
Yeah, baby, get some!
Charlie Oscar,
Gunrunner standing by.
Bring it down. Cleared hot.
Come on, Grace, move!
Down! Head down!
Come on, come on! Down!
Solid hits.
Solid rocks on target.
Screw this.
Hey! What the hell
are you doing?
I didn't sign up
for this shit!
Repeat. Ripple fire.
Go! Go! Go!
No, no, get back!
Back!
Come on!
Come on, move! Move!
That's good work, people.
First round's on me tonight.
Let's boogie.
Dragon coming left, heading home.
Gunrunner coming left.
Thunder copies.
Rider section copies.
Neytiri!
I'm sorry.
Get away.
Get away!
Get away from here!
Never come back!
Pull the plug.
No, you can't do that!
You can't do that!
Calm down! Calm down!
No! Please!
I was a warrior who dreamed
he could bring peace.
Sooner or later, though,
you always have to wake up.
Let's go!
Put him down!
You murderer!
What's going on, brother?
Long time no see.
Hey.
Personally, I don't feel these
tree-hugging traitors deserve steak.
They get steak?
That's bullshit. Let me see that.
Yeah. You know what that is. Down.
Trudy!
All the way down.
Max!
Trudy, fire up the ship! Go!
Here.
Clear. Come on.
Here you go.
Max, stay here. I need someone
on the inside I can trust.
Okay. Go.
Clear.
Come on, baby.
Colonel? Sir?
I got a situation here.
It's Samson 1-6.
Unauthorized engine start.
3!
Come on!
Mask on!
Gas, gas, gas!
I'm taking fire!
Let's go!
Grab my hand!
Come on, we're in. Let's go!
Come on, let's go!
Let's go, go!
Colonel!
Yeah! Yeah!
All right! Yes!
Crap.
Everybody all right back there?
Yeah, baby!
Norm, you good?
Yeah!
This is gonna ruin my whole day.
Grace is hit!
What?
Get the trauma kit.
Trauma kit!
Keep the pressure on,
Grace.
Trauma kit's forward,
on the bulkhead.
Hang on, Grace.
Doesn't matter.
It's fine.
You're good to go.
Take it up!
Hold on. I'm pulling pitch.
You're clear!
Just keep going north.
Get us deep in the mountains.
Copy that.
Norm, you all good up there?
Yep! Still here.
Well, at least they can't track us up here.
Not this far into the Vortex.
It's strongest at the
Tree of Souls, right?
Yeah.
Good. 'Cause that's
where we're going.
Ouch.
You big baby.
We're moving.
I'm gonna get you
some help, Grace.
I'm a scientist, remember?
I don't believe in fairy tales.
The People can help you.
I know it.
Why would they help us?
The People say Eywa will provide.
With no home, no hope,
there was only
one place they could go.
Link's running.
What's the plan here, Jake?
There's no plan.
Tsu'tey is Olo'eyktan now.
He's not gonna let you near that place.
I gotta try.
Launching.
Outcast.
Betrayer.
Alien.
I was in the place
the eye does not see.
I needed their help,
and they needed mine.
But to ever
face them again,
I was gonna have to take it
to a whole new level.
Sometimes your whole life
boils down to one insane move.
There's something we gotta do.
You're not gonna like it.
Yah!
The way I had it figured,
Toruk is the baddest cat in the sky.
Nothing attacks him.
Easy, boy.
So why would he ever look up?
But that was just a theory.
Toruk Macto?
I See you.
I was afraid, Jake.
For my people.
I'm not anymore.
You are Olo'eyktan,
and you are a great warrior.
I can't do this without you.
Toruk Macto,
I will fly with you.
My friend is dying.
Grace is dying.
I beg the help of Eywa.
Look where we are, Grace.
I need to take some samples.
The Great Mother may choose
to save all that she is
in this body.
Is that possible?
She must pass through
the eye of Eywa and return.
But, Jakesully,
she is very weak.
Hang on, Grace.
They're gonna fix you up.
Jake.
Grace.
I'm with her, Jake.
She's real!
Grace? Grace, please. Grace!
What's happening?
Grace!
Did it work?
Her wounds were too great.
It was not enough time.
She is with Eywa now.
With your permission,
I will speak now.
You would honor me
by translating.
The Sky People
have sent us a message
that they can take
whatever they want
and no one can stop them.
Well, we will send them
a message.
You ride out as fast as
the wind can carry you.
You tell the other clans
to come.
You tell them Toruk Macto
calls to them.
And you fly now
with me!
My brothers!
Sisters!
And we will show
the Sky People
that they cannot take
whatever they want,
and that this,
this is our land!
Yah!
We rode out to the 4 winds.
To the horse clans
of the plain.
Back to the stars!
To the ikran people
of the Eastern Sea.
For our children's children!
When Toruk Macto
called them, they came.
Yah!
Everyone on this base,
every one of you,
is fighting for survival.
That's a fact!
There's an aboriginal horde out
there massing for an attack.
Now, these orbital
images tell me
that the hostiles' numbers
have gone from a few hundred
to well over 2,000 in one day.
And more are pouring in.
In a week's time,
there could be 20,000 of them.
At that point, they will overrun
our perimeter.
Well, that's not
gonna happen!
Our only security lies
in pre-emptive attack.
We will fight
terror with terror.
Now, the hostiles believe that
this mountain stronghold of theirs
is protected by their...
Their deity.
And when we destroy it,
we will blast a crater
in their racial memory so deep
that they won't come within 1,000 klicks
of this place ever again.
And that, too, is a fact.
Yeah! Yeah.
Jake, it's crazy here.
It's full mobilization.
They're rigging the shuttle
as a bomber.
They've got these huge pallets
of mine explosives.
It's for some kind
of shock-and-awe campaign.
Fricking daisy cutters!
Quaritch has taken over.
He's rolling, and there's no stopping him.
When?
0600 tomorrow.
Max! Max! I gotta go.
We're screwed!
And I was hoping for
some sort of tactical plan
that didn't involve martyrdom.
We're going up against gunships
with bows and arrows.
I have 15 clans out there.
That's over 2,000 warriors.
Now, we know these mountains.
We fly them. You fly them.
They don't.
Their instruments
won't work up here.
Missile tracking
won't work.
They'll have to fire
a line of sight.
If they bring
the fight to us,
then we have the home-field
advantage.
You know he's gonna
commit that bomber
straight to
the Tree of Souls.
Yeah, I know.
If they get to the Tree of Souls,
it's over.
That's their direct line to Eywa,
their ancestors.
It'll destroy them.
Then I guess
we'd better stop him.
I'm probably just talking
to a tree right now.
But if you're there,
I need to give you a heads-up.
If Grace is with you,
look into her memories.
See the world
we come from.
There's no green there.
They killed their Mother.
And they're gonna do
the same here.
More Sky People
are gonna come.
They're gonna come
like a rain that never ends.
Unless we stop them.
Look, you chose me
for something.
I will stand and fight.
You know I will.
But I need a little help here.
Our Great Mother
does not take sides, Jake.
She protects only
the balance of life.
It was worth a try.
Yeah! Yeah!
That's what I'm talking about!
Yeah! Yeah! That's what
I'm talking about, man!
This is Group Leader.
We are entering the Flux Vortex.
Switch to manual flight mode.
Copy. Manual flight mode.
This is Papa Dragon.
I want this mission
high and tight.
I want to be home for dinner.
Suit Team, go.
All right, ladies,
let's bring the pain!
Move, move, move!
Bravo 1-1, move left.
Bravo 1-1 moving left.
Watch flank.
Watch formation.
Keep moving.
Roger that.
Charlie 2-1, watch your spacing.
Copy that. Over.
Eyes up. Check that overhead.
And watch those thermal scans.
All call signs, Papa has lead,
pushing to target.
Escorts, stay close
on my shuttle.
We are gonna lose
some paint in here.
Gun crews,
keep your head on a swivel.
Make no mistake, people,
they're out there.
All right, people, target in sight.
Range, 4 klicks.
Valkyrie 1-6,
get your payload ready.
Copy. Prepare to offload.
Staff Sergeant,
stage the weapon.
Roll it to the ramp!
Let's go!
Hold!
Charlie 2-1, got big movement.
Hold position.
Hold up, hold up.
We got movement
out there, 500 meters.
Charlie 2-1, hold position.
Sir, ground has movement!
Fast approaching.
Charlie Oscar, Rider section.
Firing line!
Targets closing.
Range, 400 meters.
Can't you clean it up?
No, sir.
It's the Flux.
Brother, I'm gonna
punch a hole.
You follow me through.
All aircraft, weapons free!
Weapons free!
Break right. Come around.
Light them up!
Break formation,
engage all hostiles.
Yeah! Get some!
Scorpions, pursue and destroy.
Jake! Jake!
You copy?
We're falling back!
We're getting hammered!
Copy.
Get out of there.
That's him. Get after him!
Take him out!
Light her up!
Right there!
You're not the only one
with a gun, bitch.
Keep her in your sights.
Purging. Feeding the leak.
Arming all pods.
That's it!
Seze!
Rogue 1 is hit.
I'm going in.
Sorry, Jake.
Fire.
Tsu'tey!
Brother, do you read?
Rogue 1, you copy?
Trudy!
Time to target, 2 minutes.
Valkyrie 1-6,
you are cleared and hot.
Copy, Dragon.
We are starting our bomb run.
Arm number 1!
Number 1 armed!
Ma Jake!
I read you.
Neytiri!
Seze's dead.
They are very close.
They are many.
Do not attack.
Do you read me, Neytiri?
Do not attack!
Fall back now. Get out of there!
That's an order!
Neytiri!
I got movement.
Hold position.
Something's coming.
Bravo 1-1, I got a big seating.
Turn screens over.
We got movement 200 meters.
Hold your formation.
Be ready.
Watch your flanks.
Hundred meters and closing fast.
We gotta get out of here!
Fall back! Fall back!
Move!
Fall back!
On the run! On the run!
Jake, Eywa has heard you.
Eywa has heard you!
Come on!
Fall back!
Move! Move!
Sir! All escorts are down
or falling back.
Let's get this done.
Valkyrie 1-6, this is Dragon.
Press to target.
Copy. Pressing to target.
Stand by to drop,
30 seconds.
On my mark.
2, 1, mark.
Drop! Drop! Drop!
Go, go, go!
Brace!
It's Sully.
Mask on!
Breach alarm!
Come on.
Come to papa.
Give it up, Quaritch!
It's all over.
Nothing's over
while I'm breathing.
I kind of hoped you'd say that.
Come on!
Hey, Sully, how's it feel
to betray your own race?
You think you're one of them?
Time to wake up.
Jake?
Jake.
Jake! Ma Jake!
I See you.
Subtitles: Arigon
The aliens went back
to their dying world.
Only a few were chosen to stay.
The time of great sorrow
was ending.
Toruk Macto was
no longer needed.
Well, I guess this is
my last video log.
'Cause whatever happens tonight,
either way, I'm...
I'm not gonna be coming back
to this place.
Well, I guess I'd better go.
Yeah, I don't want to be late
for my own party.
Yeah, it's my birthday, after all.
This is Jake Sully signing off.
Walking through a dream
I see you
My light in darkness
breathing hope of new life
Now I live through you
and you through me
Enchanting
I pray in my heart
That this dream never ends
I see me through your eyes
Breathing new life,
flying high
Your love shines the way
into paradise
So I offer my life
I offer my love for you
And my heart was never open
And my spirit never free
To the world
that you have shown me
But my eyes
could not envision
All the colors of love
and of life evermore
Evermore
I see me through your eyes
Flying high
Your love shines the way
into paradise
So I offer my life
as a sacrifice
I live through your love
I live
Through your life
I see you